<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christos kai kerdos. = Christ the life, and death the gain, of every true beleever: or, The life of a saint resolved into Christ, and His death into gain. Held forth clearly in a sermon preached at the late sad and solemn funeral of the right worshipful Rowland Wilson, Esq; a Member of the Parliament of England, and of the honorable Councel of State; and one of the aldermen and sheriffs of the city of London. By Obadiah Sedgvvick, B.D. and minister of the Gospel at Covent-Garden. Together with an epistle dedicatory: wherein is an exact account given upon some years more then ordinary experience of the superlative worth of this eminent servant of Christ, and of the Common-wealth. By George Cokayn, an unworthy teacher of the Gospel at Pancras Soper lane, London.</title>
            <author>Sedgwick, Obadiah, 1600?-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92849</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2368</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E599_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206326</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865498</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865498</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117743</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92849)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117743)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 92:E599[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christos kai kerdos. = Christ the life, and death the gain, of every true beleever: or, The life of a saint resolved into Christ, and His death into gain. Held forth clearly in a sermon preached at the late sad and solemn funeral of the right worshipful Rowland Wilson, Esq; a Member of the Parliament of England, and of the honorable Councel of State; and one of the aldermen and sheriffs of the city of London. By Obadiah Sedgvvick, B.D. and minister of the Gospel at Covent-Garden. Together with an epistle dedicatory: wherein is an exact account given upon some years more then ordinary experience of the superlative worth of this eminent servant of Christ, and of the Common-wealth. By George Cokayn, an unworthy teacher of the Gospel at Pancras Soper lane, London.</title>
                  <author>Sedgwick, Obadiah, 1600?-1658.</author>
                  <author>Cokayn, George, 1619-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Macock for Thomas Brewster and Gregory Moul, at the three Bibles in Pauls church-yard, neer the West end,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First three words of title are in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 30".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wilson, Rowland, 1613-1650 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117743:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117743:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ΧΡΙΣΤΟΣ ΚΑΙ ΚΕΡΔΟΣ</p>
            <p>Chriſt the Life, <hi>and</hi> Death the Gain, of Every True BELEEVER: OR, THE Life of a Saint Reſolved into Chriſt, AND His Death into Gain.</p>
            <p>Held forth clearly in a SERMON preached at the late ſad and ſolemn Funeral of the Right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Rowland Wilſon,</hi> Eſq; a Member of the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and of the honorable <hi>Councel of State;</hi> and one of the Aldermen and Sheriffs of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Obadiah Sedgvvick, B. D. and Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Covent-Garden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with an Epiſtle Dedicatory: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is an exact Account given upon ſome years more then ordinary Experience of the ſuperlative Worth of this Eminent Servant of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and of the <hi>Common-wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By George Cokayn, an unworthy Teacher of the Goſpel at <hi>Pancras</hi> Soper lane, <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Isaiah 57. 1.</bibl> 
               <hi>The righteous periſheth, and no man layeth it to heart; and merciful men are taken away, none conſidering that the righteous is taken away from the evil to come.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>Difficile eſt definire extra Chriſtum, ſitne mori utilius quam vivere: rurſum adſit Chriſtus, &amp; vitam noſtram perinde ac mortem be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedicet, ut ſit utraque nobis fauſta &amp; expetenda. <bibl>
                  <hi>Calv.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Macock</hi> for <hi>Thomas Brewſter</hi> and <hi>Gregory Moul,</hi> at the three Bibles in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, neer the Weſt end 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:117743:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117743:2"/>
            <head>To the truly Religious and ever Honored, Mrs <hi>Mary Wilſon,</hi> diſconſolate Widow to the late worthy and godly Patriot, <hi>Rowland Wilſon,</hi> Eſq; a Member of the Parliament of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and of the honorable Councel of State, and one of the Aldermen and Sheriffs of the City of <hi>London.</hi> Grace and Conſolation from God the Father, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>VIRTUOUS LADY,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is enacted by the Supream Power of Heaven and Earth, That man, the Maſter of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhould be a ſervant and a helper to the moſt contemptible creature fallen under his burden: by vertue of that Law the Ox or the Aſs might <note place="margin">Exo. 23. 5. Deu. 22. 4.</note> challenge and command help from their owners. Doth God take care of Oxen? Surely for our ſakes theſe things are written, to ſhew, that the Lord in a ſpecial manner doth oblige and command all that mention his Name, to make themſelves, to the utmoſt, comforting and refreſhing to all his people, who taste the bitterneſs, and feel the weight of an afflicted ſtate. God no ſooner hears the ſad cries and complaints of poor op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed Iſrael in Egypt, but <hi>Moſes</hi> hears the news from <note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 9, 10</note> God of his going with a preſent Meſſage of Relief to them. Nay, the Spirit himſelf, God equal with the Father and the Son, ſhall upon the ſame account be <note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 14. 16</note> ſent from Heaven, and this ſhall be the great Title he ſhall be inveſted with, <hi>viz. [The Comforter.]</hi> To comfort the Saints is a work every way ſuitable to the higheſt in Heaven or Earth to perform. When I conſider theſe things, but especially recollect the innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Obligations which are upon me from the constant flowings forth of your expreſſions of friendſhip to me, I (being for many years together your poor &amp; unworthy Servant in the things of the Goſpel) could not but in a ſpecial maner account it my duty ſolicitouſly to endeavor the bringing forth of ſomething, which through the bleſſing of God might be inſtrumental to the ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering of the darkneſs of that night which is now upon you, through the late inexpected and ſadly lamented ſetting of that Sun which did ſhine ſo gloriouſly in your Horizon. And truly amongst all other things which my thoughts endeavored to engage for your refreſhment, I found none ſo exactly calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to your condition as that incomparable peece of Gospel
<pb facs="tcp:117743:3"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by <note place="margin">Mr <hi>Ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diah Sedg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick.</hi>
               </note> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and godly Meſſenger of Chriſt at the late ſad and ſolemn Puneral of your loving and beloved Huſband. And ſeeing the reverend Author, through a modeſt and humble diſowning of himſelf, was unwilling to be Midwife to his own Birth, I have (with his conſent and leave obtained, through much importunity) made bold to preſent it to you, as that which, through the concurrence of divine bleſſing, may adminiſter exceeding abundant conſolation to your drooping and decaying Spirit. I cannot but look upon this Text and Sermon as an exact Comment upon your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>us huſband his life and death: his life was nothing elſe but a continual reſolution of all his actions and ends into Chriſt; and his death nothing elſe but a victory over ſin, and a ſure conduct into the bleſſed ſtate of eternity. And now did I not fear the further opening of the ſluces of your ſwelling paſſion, to the breaking in of an irreſistible torrent of ſadneſs upon your Spirit, I could very eaſily engage my ſelf to a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminous Diſcourſe of this nature: but leſt the lifting up of him, ſhould renew an occaſion of caſting down your Spirit, I ſhall the more briefly preſent before you, and the whole world, what in my own obſervation was always, ſince I know him, eminently deſerving in him: Whereby it will plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that the Life and Spirit both of Text and Sermon did clearly ſhew forth themſelves in him. The truth is, when I conſider the exactneſs of his carriage in all relations, I am very apt to think, that as, for a complication of all perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he while he lived was <note n="*" place="margin">Nulli ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundus.</note> ſecond to none; ſo now he is gone, there will ſcarce another appear ſecond to him. He was an incomparable Huſband to you, an excellent Man to the State, and a precious Christian to God. He was to you the ſweeteſt yoke-fellow in the world, not one of his carriages but apparent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bearing the Image of that Fountain from whence it ſprung, <hi>viz.</hi> ſtrong, wiſe and intire affections. He loved ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly, and yet ruled diſcreetly. You had, I am ſure, all you deſired, which was his heart, but not his head. He was <note place="margin">Plin: nat. Hiſt. li. 10. cap. 62.</note> never like the hee-viper, which put his head into the ſhee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vipers mouth. What God gave him to keep, he kept, and what God gave him to communicate to you, he did punctually per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form. The truth is, both of you in this were ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct Diſciples
<pb facs="tcp:117743:3"/>
to <hi>Moſes,</hi> always confining your ſelves to your proper apparel. That perfection methoughts which was amongst the reſt, as the Sun in the midſt of the Stars, was his unparalleld con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedneſs in the want of children, like <hi>Abraham</hi> in <hi>this,</hi> that he never in the leaſt grieved you by abraiding you, but excell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Abraham</hi> in <hi>this,</hi> that he never, either to God or man, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becomingly complained of the want of a mercy ſo naturally deſireable, but ſtill expreſſed his ſence of the full and compleat making up of that tryal, next to Christ, in your ſelf: And when it pleaſed God to lay a real foundation of hopes of enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that bleſſing, he was indeed, like a Beleever, affected with the goodneſs and Providence of God, but not at all ſo tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, as if he had not been long before crucified to it. And when it pleaſed God to return and blast thoſe hopes, he carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it like one that deſired no will but Gods might be accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated. He expreſſed as much joy in his diſappointment, as ever he did in his expectation. He always ſaid in that neer tryal, <hi>Not my Will, but thine be done.</hi> He made it the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of his delight to ſcatter any cloud of trouble that reſted upon your Spirit; and though he naturally rejoyced in his own melancholly, yet the least ſymptome of ſadneſs in you was a burthen too heavy for him to bear. The truth is, all his carriages in this relation have left behind them this true te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony of him, that he rather made moſt worthy preſidents, then confined himſelf to the best examples. But I fear I have been too long in ſurveying his perfections in this rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and in commending him as a huſband, I have diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended my ſelf as a friend, in adding too much fuel to the burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing flame of your paſſionate affection. I ſhall therefore rather bury him as your huſband, and preſent him to you again as the huſband of the Common-wealth; to which indeed he was truly marryed, cheerfully ſpending himſelf in a continual faithful purſute of the Affairs thereof. He was a <hi>Timotheus</hi> in the <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 20. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Common-wealth, <hi>naturally caring for their State:</hi> He was indeed by the Providence of God in a very ſhort time called to ſeveral places of highest Honor and greateſt Truſt amongst us, wherein he always behaved himſelf, though as a Ruler over the perſons of men, yet as a true Servant to the good of men: As in his private, ſo in his publike capacity, no ones
<pb facs="tcp:117743:4"/>
leſs then his own. He ſtill deſired that Juſtice might be as a River, and never coveted, to pale it in as a pond <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate uſe. He delighted immediately to ſerve the publike, and at the moſt but collaterally himſelf: Yea, many a time hath he vigorouſly and heartily appeared againſt his own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate intereſt, that he might approve himſelf a faithful friend to the Publique. I know nothing he got by all his Service, except <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pluta.</hi> in the life of <hi>Thra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ybu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus.</hi> p. 12 34.</note> 
               <hi>Thraſybulus</hi> his reward, a crown of two branches, Bays, whereby he never contracted the peoples envy, but to his laſt had an interest in all mens good word and affection. And (which was the crown of all) he ever ſtood firm to his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and could never be juſtly numbred amongst them <hi>who were given to change,</hi> always abhorring to wear that Glove which would fit both hands: If at any time he went with the ſtream, it was becauſe the ſtream went with him; and ſtil as the tyde turned, he owned his Principles, and boldly adventured to ſwim againſt it. No man can charge him to be like the bull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſh, which always waves with the wind; but all that knew him, can, without falſhood or flattery, affirm, that nothing could move him but Reaſon and Honeſty. The truth is, he was in this capacity a man ſo excelling, that every one was ambitious (as they were about <hi>Homer)</hi> to prove him to be his <note place="margin">Homer.</note> Countryman. But why do I ſtay ſo long in this, which, to the judgment and experience of his fellow Worthies, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to the whole Nation and City, was ſo certain and infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible; I rather deſcend to ſpeak to his ſpiritual part, as he knew, owned, loved and obeyed Jeſus Chriſt, and truly in this I know none that profeſs the Name of God in the way of the Gospel, but may be glad to have ſuch a Copy to write after. I have obſerved ſeveral things in him as a Saint, which I never ſaw met together in ſo much perfection in any man of his time.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He was a Real Chriſtian; he was ſuch a Chriſtian, as <note n="a" place="margin">Seneca.</note> 
               <hi>Seneca</hi> was a Philoſopher, <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Plut.</hi> in the life of <hi>Seneca.</hi>
               </note> more ſo in deed, then in name; though his face, with <hi>Moſes, did always ſhine,</hi> yet especially, with the Kings daughter, <hi>he was all glorious within:</hi> He much delighted to be beſt to God, and to his boſom friends. His integrity was his perfection. I may ſay of him (and I know the Lord ſaith the ſame) as God ſpake of <hi>Job,</hi> in every
<pb facs="tcp:117743:4"/>
condition, that there was <hi>none like him in the earth, a perfect</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Job 1. 8. Job 2. 3. Gen 25. 27. Vid. <hi>car.</hi> in <hi>Job</hi> 1. 8.</note> 
               <hi>and an upright man, one that feareth God, and eſcheweth evil:</hi> That which is here called <hi>perfect,</hi> in <hi>Jacobs</hi> Character is call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>plain,</hi> ſo that the plain heart is the perfect heart, which was indeed the unparalleld perfection of this Worthy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He was a Humble Christian; the higher he was in Gods account, the lower ſtill in his own: He knew too much of God, as not to know himſelf: He often ſpake in the language of <hi>Job; I have heard of thee by the hearing of the ear, but</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Job 42 5. 6.</note> 
               <hi>now mine eye ſeeth thee; wherefore I abhor my ſelf, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in duſt and aſhes.</hi> He was never like the Phariſee, who lived far from neighbors, and ſo was neceſſitated to commend himſelf. He did indeed for his time very much for God, yet <note place="margin">Col. 3. 12. 1 Pet. 5. 5. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>humilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem animi vobis in fixam ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bete.</hi>
               </note> was he never heard to ſay, <hi>Come ſee my zeal for the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> He always obſerved the Apoſtles Rule, <hi>to put on humbleneſs of mind, and to be clothed with humility;</hi> for all that ever converſed with him, did, from the ſweetneſs of his carriage, truly conclude him to be a man humble in Spirit. In the midſt of all his honours he was rather preſſed down with the weight of them, then puffed up with the blast of them. When he was at the higheſt, the poor, which received the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel, he ſtill with much delight received as his familiars and equals; yea, with S. <hi>Paul,</hi> rather accounting himſelf the <hi>leaſt,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15 9 Ephe. 3 8. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Miaimorum minimo</hi> Bez. <hi>Non jacto dignitatem meam fatcor me minimum eſse omnium Sanctorum.</hi> Pelica.</note> yea <hi>leſs then the leaſt of all Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. He was a Sober Christian: though he much enquired into ſpiritual Myſteries, yet he never was wiſe above what was written. I never knew him but a great Lover of the Scriptures, and a ſpecial Admirer of that they teſtified of, <hi>viz.</hi> the Glorious Myſtery of Christ Crucified. He was never ſo ſuperstitious, as againſt clearer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ght, wilfully to retain dark and worm-eaten Principles; neither was he ſo ſlight, as upon every ſpecious ſhew to ſorego a wel experimented ſerious truth, to embrace a notional nothing. I am privy to many temptations of this kind, which he often wraſtled with: But this I know, that down-right plain truths, ſuch as <hi>Peter</hi> preached, <hi>Acts 2.</hi> (an expreſſion he often loved to uſe) were more acceptable and ſweet to him, then all the empty high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flown
<pb facs="tcp:117743:5"/>
nations and ſpeculations which this age, above all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, hath uſhered into the world. God gave him the mercy of a plain heart, and that heart delighted in pure and plain <note place="margin">Simile gaudet ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mili.</note> truth. I have heard, that there is in Scotland a floating Iſland, that if the Seaman cast his Anchor there, the Land will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably carry away his Ship. This excellent Servant of the Lord did never caſt the Anchor of his Soul upon ſuch an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain thing, but upon Christ, who is <hi>yeſterday, and to day, and the ſame for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. He was a Believing Chriſtian: <hi>The life which he lived</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 2. 20.</note> 
               <hi>in the fleſh was by the faith of the Son of God.</hi> He was clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taught of God that rare art of going out of himſelf, and acting in another. Hence it came to paſs, that what he did <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deus magis delectatur adverbi is quam no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus.</hi> Heb. 11. 5.</note> was not only good in the matter, but alſo in the manner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance, with which * God is well pleaſed. This is the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony which the Apoſtle gives of <hi>Enoch,</hi> that <hi>by faith he ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God.</hi> And the grand thing which God will take notice of at the laſt day, ſhall be the acting of Saints in a holy and ſpiritual manner: <hi>Well done good and faithful Servant, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 21 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> id eſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Bez. Iob 21. 15. <hi>Quid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>iemus?</hi> Iun. Mal. 3 14.</note> 
               <hi>thou into the Joy of thy Lord.</hi> His faith led him forth to do all that he did ſtill out of pure and entire affection to God, and the things themſelves. He never ſerved God for profit, but for pleaſure; not like thoſe which desperately ſaid, <hi>What profit ſhall we have if we pray unto him?</hi> nor like thoſe who much ſpeak the ſame language, <hi>What profit is it that we have kept his Ordinance?</hi> Nay, rather he accounted the work it ſelf, wherein he enjoyed ſweet and intimate Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Chriſt, as ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ient wages. He delighted much to be near Chriſt, to ſee his face, and to hear his voyce: It was his frequent expreſſion, How dull is that Sermon or Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance to me, wherein I cannot ſee or meet with Jeſus Chriſt! Chriſt ſtill was the Ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er of all his thoughts, which made him ſo little to be taken with this world, that he did not ſo much as careleſly mind the inheritance God gave him here, but ſtill delighted to accommodate his thoughts with better objects: It was but a trouble to him to think of living to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy that which he was heir to, he ſtill rather deſired <hi>to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, and to be with Chriſt,</hi> which he accounted <hi>beſt of all</hi> for him: Though his time was but ſhort in this world, yet he
<pb facs="tcp:117743:5"/>
thought it extream long till he was in the arms of his Saviour. It made him to bear his laſt ſickneſs with much patience and cheerfulneſs, becauſe he thought after that ſickneſs he ſhould be well to eternity: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon that account, though he was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times full of pain, yet he was always full of peace, inſomuch that the very day before he dyed, being asked by a friend, whom he loved, How it was now with his Spirit? his anſwer preſently was, I have now no trouble to wraſtle with, but the unwillingneſs of thoſe that are dear to me to ſubmit to the Will of the Lord concerning me, expreſſing in himſelf much joy and ſatisfaction in his expectation of the ſudden ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of Gods good Pleaſure, wherein the Lord not many hours after did fully gratifie his longing deſires, and even in the ſtrength and vigour of his underſtanding and parts he ſweetly fell aſleep in the Lord. And now, <hi>Oh that my head were waters, and mine eyes a fountain of tears, that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 9 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> 
               <hi>I might weep day and night</hi> for ſo irrepairable a loſs. I know nothing here can now take my heart, when the righteous are thus ſadly taken away. But I muſt correct my ſelf, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire into the Wilderneſs, and weep bitterly, where none ſhall witneſs it, or be prejudiced by it. Therefore now ſeeing God hath determined his own Will, my great buſineſs is in the ſtrength of Chriſt to ſpeak to your conſolation (ſweet Lady) who have the deepeſt ſhare in this ſad loſs. The truth is, the Lord hath taken from you the most ſuitable and choyceſt <note place="margin">Quum non ſatis natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae, neque Gloriae, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quae patriae vix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſset.</note> mercy you had below himſelf, and that in the midſt of your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of it; when the flower in your boſom was moſt fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant, it pleaſed the Lord that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it ſhould be withered. God took him away before he had lived half long enough to any relation; but the Lord hath done it, and it is good to be ſilent in his Will: Your buſineſs now is to ſee and receive the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up of this loſs in Chriſt, who is not only a Father to the fatherleſs, but alſo a Huſband to the Widow: <note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 54 5.</note> 
               <hi>Thy Maker is thy Husband.</hi> There are four things wherein the Lord doth manifeſt to you his tender ſenſe of your condition.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He executes all your Judgment for you; <hi>He is the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſa 68. 5. <hi>Defenſor viduarum.</hi> Iun. <hi>Spei ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laris ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutis domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſibi templum fabricat.</hi> Aug.</note> 
               <hi>Judg:</hi> Hers in a peculiar manner. God was ſo good under the Law, as <hi>to</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Deu. 10. 81.</note> 
               <hi>execute the judgment of the widow;</hi> much more is he ſo now under the Gospel: Whether you are Plaintiff or Defendant, ſeeing the Judg is yours, the Cauſe cannot but be yours alſo.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb facs="tcp:117743:6"/>2. He eſtabliſheth mercies to you: When a huſband dyes, the very pillars of the houſe are broken; God then appears and eſtabliſheth all again: ſo that now what the widow hath, though never ſo little, is more ſure to her then to any one elſe: <note place="margin">Pro. 15. 25 <hi>Conſtituit terminum viduae.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>un. 1 King. 17. 16.</note> 
               <hi>* He eſtabliſheth the border of the widow.</hi> It was <hi>the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows</hi> oyl in the cruſe, and <hi>the widows</hi> meal in the barrel, which did not waſte.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He threatens all that afflict you; He proclaims to all the world what he will do againſt them who do the leaſt thing againſt you: Read often that place, <hi>Exod. 22. 22, 23, 24.</hi> Yea, if any do but ſo much as <hi>vex</hi> you, God numbers it in the <note place="margin">Ezek 22. 7</note> Catalogue of their great prevocations.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He looks upon it as a ſignel act of goodneſs in all that ſhew mercy to you: He looks upon it as that wherein all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Curare &amp; pro virili ſublevare.</hi> Bez. <hi>Jor.</hi> 49. 11</note> is ſwallowed up: <hi>This is pure Religion, to viſit the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs and widows in their affliction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now from all this diſcovery of Gods goodneſs to you, what is it that God may juſtly expect and challenge from you, but the caſting of your ſelf by faith upon him? God encourageth you to it: <hi>Let their widows truſt in me.</hi> Now earth is blaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and withered to you, whom ſhould you fly to, but him in whom the life and fulneſs of what you have loſt ſtill do abide and continue? What Earth cannot repair, Heaven can. Oh that God would therefore by this dispenſation take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to lead you forth into further experiences of himſelf, that you might, while you drink down this bitter cup, <hi>taſte alſo and ſee that the Lord is gracious.</hi> This I know will be your only relief, and that which in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e will certainly ſcatter that cloud of ſadneſs which indeed at preſent reſts with too great dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs upon your Spirit, which the Lord, by the manifestation of himſelf, will in his time totally diſpel: In the mean while, let that ſweet Scripture as a companion reſt with you: <hi>Unto the upright there ariſeth light in the darkneſs: he is gracious, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 112. 4.</note> 
               <hi>full of compaſſion, and righteous.</hi> That the Marrow and Spirit of this Text may be your Portion, is the unceſſan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>LADY,</salute> 
               <signed> Your poor Orator at the Throne of Grace, and unworthy Servant in the Work of the Goſpel. GEORGE COKAY</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>Apr. 18. 1650.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117743:6"/>
            <head>PHILIPPIANS 1. 21. <hi>To Me to Live, is Christ; and to Dye, is Gain.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Shall not trouble you with the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence, nor with the various Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of theſe words, which do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of Two parts: 1. The Scope or End of a Chriſtians Life, <hi>[To me to live, is Christ.]</hi> 2. The Hope and Fruit of a Chriſtians Death, <hi>[And to dye, is Gain.]</hi> A Real Chriſtian is (of all men) in the Beſt Condition: For if he lives, he Gets; and if he dyes, he Gains. None Improve Life well, and None Inrich themſelves by Death, but Beleeving <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> From theſe Two parts there are two Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, unto which I intend to ſpeak at this time: 1. The Firſt is, That the Life of a Real Chriſtian is Reſolved into Chriſt. 2. The Second is, That
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117743:7"/>
the Death of a Real Chriſtian is Reſolved into Gain. I begin with the Firſt of theſe.</p>
            <p>That the Life of a Real Chriſtian is Reſolved in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">1 <hi>Propo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> Chriſt; <hi>(To me to live, is Chriſt.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Life of a Chiſtian hath a Four-fold refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence unto Chriſt. Chriſt is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Principium,</hi> The Principle or Fountain of His Life: All Spiritual Life is Firſt in Chriſt, and Next in us; As the life of the Branches is Firſt in the Root, and from thence Imparted to the Branches: <hi>I Am the Vine, Ye Are the Branches; Joh.</hi> 15. 5.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Objectum:</hi> Chriſt is the Object upon which the Chriſtian lives; <hi>I live by the Faith of the Son of God, Gal.</hi> 2. 20. As the Ordinary Man lives upon his Food, ſo the Spiritual Man lives upon his Chriſt. Whatſoever makes for Life, For that doth the Beleever live on Chriſt, who indeed is the onely All of Life, and for Life, unto his Soul.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Regula:</hi> Chriſt is the Rule and Square of a Chriſtians Life; <hi>He that Abideth in him, Ought himſelf alſo to walk, As he walked, 1 Joh.</hi> 2. 6. Hence thoſe expreſſions, <hi>My ways which be In Chriſt, 1 Cor. 4. 17. Your Good Converſation In Chriſt, 1 Pet. 3. 16. Be Followers of me, As I am of Chriſt, 1 Cor. 11. 1. Walk in love, As Christ alſo hath loved us, Eph.</hi> 5. 2. The Life of Chriſt is the Copy, and the Life of a Chriſtian is a Line written after that Copy: The Life of Chriſt is the Seal, and the Life of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is the Character or Expreſſion of that Seal;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117743:7"/>
His Life is (in this ſence alſo) The <hi>Manifeſtation of the life of Chriſt, 2 Cor.</hi> 4. 10.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Finis,</hi> or <hi>Scopus:</hi> Chriſt is the End unto which, and for which, a Chriſtian doth live. The Life of a Chriſtian, (that is) the Courſe of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, the Courſe of his Thoughts and Deſigns, the Courſe of his Deſires and Affections, the Courſe of his Endevors and Labors, All the Courſe of his Life is directed unto Chriſt; it is ſubordinate and ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Glorifying of Chriſt. <hi>None of us</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle in <hi>Rom. 14. 7, 8.) liveth to Himſelf, and No man dyeth to Himſelf: For whether we live, we live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord; and whether we dye, we dye unto the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> A man lives unto himſelf, who ſets up <note place="margin">Qui ſe unum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicit.</note> himſelf As the End of his living, and onely regards himſelf. You have a ſuitable expreſſion with this in <hi>Pſal. 49. 18. Whiles he lived, he Bleſſed his own Soul:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hetib le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>napſiſelſo.</note> 
               <hi>(i. e.)</hi> All that he Aimed at, was to pleaſe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, and enrich, and increaſe himſelf. So on the contrary, To live unto the Lord, to live unto Chriſt, is Not onely to Set up the Will of Chriſt As the Rule of Life, But Alſo to Set up the Glory and Advantages of Chriſt, As the Superlative Aim or End of Life.</p>
            <p>You have the like paſſage in 2 <hi>Cor. 5. 15. He dyed for All, that They which live, ſhould not henceforth live unto themſelves, But unto Him which dyed for them, and roſe again.</hi> The Apoſtle doth here make a Parallel and Reciprocal Intention 'twixt Chriſt and Chriſtians. The Intention of Chriſt in His Death was Their Good, <hi>(He dyed for them;)</hi> and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117743:8"/>
of Chriſt in His Reſurrection was Their Good, <hi>(He Roſe again for them; He was delivered for Our Offences, and was Raiſed again for Our Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, Rom.</hi> 4. 25.) Chriſt did not live for Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but For Us; Chriſt did not dye for Himſelf, but For Us; Chriſt did not Riſe for Himſelf, but For Us: He intended Our Good in All theſe. And ſo Reciprocally, Chriſtians ſhould, in their whole courſe of life, Not intend Themſelves, but Chriſt; Not live unto themſelves, but unto Chriſt: Our Good and Salvation was His End, and His Honor and Glory ſhould be Our End.</p>
            <p>Now, for the further clearing of this Aſſertion, I ſhall endeavor to demonſtrate two Things: Namely,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That Real Chriſtians do propound Jeſus Chriſt As the Scope and End of their Life.</item>
               <item>2. Why they do ſo, and why they ſhould do ſo.</item>
            </list>
            <p>That Real Chriſtians do Propound Jeſus Chriſt <note place="margin">1.</note> As the End of their living, will plainly Appear, if you do ſeriously conſider, That Jeſus Chriſt hath All thoſe peculiar Influences and Operations upon their Hearts, which Any Chief End hath upon eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man who ſets it up, As So, unto Himſelf. That which is Any Mans Chief End, it hath Six Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It doth <hi>Excitare;</hi> it ſets a man to work, it <note place="margin">Finis mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet ad A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendum.</note> ſets the wheels going; it doth awaken and ſtir every Faculty of the Soul, and makes them Active. If a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117743:8"/>
Mans Heart be Set on Any part of the World As his Chief End, ſuppoſe it be Honor with <hi>Haman,</hi> or Pleaſure with <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> or Riches with <hi>Dives;</hi> why, preſently All the Soul is drawn out, and works for that worldly End: The Minde thinks and plods, the Will deſires and ſtirs, the Affections long and thirſt, and the whole in that man acts and labors towards that End. In like manner Jeſus Chriſt (who is the Great End of a Chriſtians Life) hath a very ſtrong and influential virtue upon the Heart of a Chriſtian: The Glory of Chriſt quickens, ſtirs, draws out his Soul; <hi>The love of Chriſt conſtrains us,</hi> ſaid <hi>Paul</hi> in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 14. It doth urge us, puts us <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Vid. <hi>Beza.</hi> in locum.</note> Forward, wholy poſſeſſeth us, Rules us, diſpoſeth of us, carries us on as men poſſeſſed with a vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency of Spirit; or as a Ship which ſtrong winds do drive apace. If Jeſus Chriſt, if any Inter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt of his be concerned, the Chriſtian looks on himſelf ſo concerned therein, that he cannot but put out him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Act.</hi> 4. 17, 18. The Councel there threaten and charge the Apoſtles, <hi>That henceforth they ſhould ſpeak to no man in the Name of Chriſt:</hi> What An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer make <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> to this? See Verſ. 20. <hi>We cannot but ſpeak the things which we have ſeen and heard,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) Alaſs! do you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand us to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lent for Chriſt? Why, it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that we ſhould not publiſh Chriſt, and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie Chriſt: We cannot but ſpeak for him, and do for him: You may as well charge the Sun to ſtand ſtill, as charge us to be ſilent for Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:117743:9"/>2. That which is a Mans Chief End, it doth <hi>Commenſurare;</hi> it doth ſquare, and ſuit, and fit all <note place="margin">Finis eſt Regul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> his actions and ways with a conformable Subſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency and Reſpectiveneſs unto that end. There is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways a Proportion and Harmony 'twixt an End, and Actions looking at that End. And therefore is it, That according unto mens ſeveral Ends, there are ſeveral ſorts of Actions; and always thoſe are layd aſide, which are inconſiſtent with, or repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to our ends; and thoſe only are choſen, which are ſubordinate unto them.</p>
            <p>Now thus it is between Chriſt and Chriſtians: Chriſt is their End; and it appears by this that He is ſo, Becauſe all their actions of Life, in the courſe of it, are faſhioned and ſhaped with a reſpect to Chriſt. Chriſt is the Meaſure of their ways and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: <hi>We can do Nothing Againſt the Truth, but For the Truth,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, 2 Cor.</hi> 13. 8. So a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an can do Nothing (knowingly) againſt Chriſt, but for Chriſt. He conſiders of his actions and ways; Will theſe make for Chriſt, or Not? As the Eagle doth with her young ones, thoſe of them which can look upon the Sun, ſhe owns, and thoſe that cannot, ſhe throws off: So doth the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an on ways and ſervices; ſuch as directly look at the Glory of Chriſt, he embraces and proſecutes; but ſuch as are contrary unto Chriſt, he rejects and forbears, as unworthy of his practiſe, becauſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to Chriſts Honor.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That which is a Mans Chief End, it doth <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitare;</hi> the Thoughts and Apprehenſions of it do
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117743:9"/>
make the Services and Employments of the Man very eaſie and light unto him, which otherwiſe would be very heavy and tedious. You could not drudg ſo as ſome men do, nor break your ſleep, nor go to bed ſo late, and riſe ſo early, nor endure ſuch Cares, not converſe with ſo many Troubles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet they make Nothing of theſe, becauſe Their End is to be Rich and Great; Therefore theſe things are not burthenſom, but eaſie to them.</p>
            <p>Thus is it with a Chriſtian who makes Chriſt his End: Natural men do wonder how a Chriſtian can ſpend ſo much time in Holy Meditations, in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Duties, in Spiritual Studies and Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; that he can venture ſo much for Chriſt, endure ſo much for Chriſt, part with, and loſe ſo much, and ſuffer ſo much for Chriſt! And yet all theſe are eaſie to the Chriſtian, becauſe Chriſt is His End: <hi>I am ready,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, not to be bound onely, but to dye at Ieruſalem for the Name of the Lord Ieſus, Act.</hi> 21. 13. The hardeſt Actions and the ſharpeſt paſsions were eaſie to him, ſo that Chriſt might be magnified.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That which is a Mans Great End, that ſame <note place="margin">Finis dat Amabilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</note> doth <hi>Delectare,</hi> it doth delight him; and it makes all the ways conducing unto it, delightful. It is a Truth, that <hi>(Summus Finis eſt Summum Bonum)</hi> a Mans chief End is a Mans chief Good; and then you know that whatſoever is a Mans chiefeſt Good, the ſame is a Mans chiefeſt Delight.</p>
            <p>There is Nothing in the World which is a more abſolute Delight and Joy to a Chriſtian, then Jeſus
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117743:10"/>
Chriſt; for whoſe ſake even the moſt Bitter Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices become moſt pleaſing and contenting. They, in the tenth of the <hi>Hebrews, took Joyfully the ſpoiling of their Goods,</hi> becauſe this was for Chriſt; and the Martyrs could ſing and embrace the very flames, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this was for Chriſt. And as that Martyr was troubled that he had but one Life to loſe for Chriſt, ſo a Real Chriſtian is Never<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Troubled that there is ſo much to be done for Chriſt, but rather that he hath done ſo little for Chriſt. And as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpake of the paths of Wiſdom, <hi>(Prov.</hi> 3. 17.) that <hi>All her ways were ways of pleaſantneſs, and all her paths were peace;</hi> That the Chriſtian can ſay of all the ways and ſervices of, and for Chriſt, they are his meat and drink, the Joy, and Delight, and Rejoyce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Heart: Or as Chriſt ſpake to His Father concerning the work of our Redemption, <hi>Lo, I come; I delight to do thy Will, Pſal.</hi> 40. 7, 8. The ſame can a Real Chriſtian ſpeak concerning Chriſt, and his ſervices for Chriſt. O Lord Jeſus! No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is dearer to me then thy ſelf; Thou art my Love, and all that is to be done for thee is lovely; Thou art my Delight, and all that I can do for thee, becauſe it is for Thee, is therefore delightful. It is my Salvation that Thou art my Chriſt; It is my Honor that I am Thy Servant; It is my Heaven in Heaven to live with Thee; and it is my Heaven on Earth to live unto Thee.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That which is a Mans Great End, it doth <hi>Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etare;</hi> it is His Enough, it is his Center: He looks not beyond it, for it is His Bound; and He moves
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117743:10"/>
not beyond it, for it is His Reſt; He is at his Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys End (at the End of All his Deſigns, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and Travels,) when he attains unto it, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joys it. Thus it is 'twixt Chriſt and a Chriſtian; There is Nothing but Chriſt, and there is No more but Chriſt, with him: Leſs then Chriſt makes him Reſtleſs, and the Fruition of Chriſt makes him Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied. If he can Get Chriſt, this is Portion E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; and if he can Glorifie Chriſt, this is Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor Enough.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shew us the Father</hi> (ſaid <hi>Philip) and it ſufficeth.</hi> Or as <hi>Jacob</hi> about <hi>Joſeph, It is Enough, Joſeph is yet Alive.</hi> Or as <hi>David, Return unto Thy Reſt, O my Soul; for the Lord hath dealt bountifully with thee.</hi> So, Chriſt gets ground in my Heart, and the Kingdom of Chriſt is advanced in the World: His Kingdom and Mountain is exalted above All the Kingdoms and Mountains in the World; This my Joy therefore is Fulfilled.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Laſtly, That which is a Mans Great End, that ſame doth <hi>Compenſare;</hi> If he can but compaſs that, it is His Recompence, it makes a full Amends for All his cares, and pains, and labors. So doth the Glory of Chriſt abundantly Recompence All the Services of a Chriſtian. As when a Poor Soul hath been panting and looking after Chriſt, if at length he findes him, <hi>(I found him whom my Soul loveth, Cant.</hi> 3.) this makes a Full Amends for All his Tears, and Prayings, and Waitings: So doth this of the Magnifying of Chriſt; If Chriſt be ſet up in his Throne, the Chriſtian then Repents not, O
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117743:11"/>
No; This is Reward enough for All that ever he hath done or ſuffered for Chriſt. And thus you have the Firſt Part demonſtrated unto you, That Real Chriſtians do propound and ſet up Jeſus Chriſt as the Scope and End of their Life: Their Life is bound up in His Life. Nothing lives, unleſs Chriſt lives. And this is the very ſum of their All, to be Servants with their All to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I now proceed unto the Second Part, Namely, <note place="margin">2.</note> Why Real Chriſtians do live, and ſhould live unto Chriſt? There are Five Reaſons for that, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you to weigh them well.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You are Chriſts, Not onely by Gift, <hi>(Thou gaveſt them me, Joh.</hi> 17. 6.) Nor onely by Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>(I will marry thee to my Self, Hoſea</hi> 2. 19.) But alſo by Purchaſe; Therefore you ſhould live unto your <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you were <hi>Chriſts</hi> onely by way of Donation, you ſhould live unto Him: What is Given to Him, that is to be uſed for Him. If you were <hi>Chriſts</hi> onely by way of Relation, you ſhould live unto Him. The Inferior part of the Relation is for the uſe and ſervice of the Superior part of the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 9. But beſides theſe, you are <hi>Chriſts</hi> by way of Redemption and Purchaſe. <hi>You Are Not your own; For you Are Bought with a Price: therefore Glorifie God in your Body, and in your Spirit, which are Gods: 1 Cor.</hi> 6. 19, 20.</p>
            <p>Mark the Apoſtle in this place; He ſaith to <hi>Chriſtians, You Are Not Your Own!</hi> Why, whoſe are They then? They are <hi>Chriſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> And How come
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117743:11"/>
they to be Chriſts? He tells them how, <hi>Ye Are Bought with a Price:</hi> And what of that? <hi>Therefore Glorifie God, &amp;c.</hi> If the Land be my Purchaſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhould Not the Fruit of that Land be my Benefit? Chriſtians they are Chriſts Purchaſe, <hi>He purchaſed them by his own Blood, Act.</hi> 20. 28. And therefore All the Rent of their Lives muſt be payd in unto his Glory.</p>
            <p>Ah Chriſtians! It coſt Jeſus Chriſt very dear to Redeem your Life from Death; The Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your Souls was the coſtlieſt Purchaſe that ever was made; Ye were <hi>Redeemed with the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Blood of Chriſt, 1 Pet.</hi> 1. 19. This was the Price. It did coſt Chriſt His Life to Save your Life; and ſhould he Not have That Life which he purchaſed by His Life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea, and by His Death? <hi>Quicquid es, debes Creanti; Quicquid potes, debes Redimenti,</hi> ſaid <hi>Bernard:</hi> Whatſoever thou Art, Thou oweſt to Him who made thee; and whatſoever thou Haſt, Thou oweſt to Him who Redeemed thee.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Jeſus Chriſt is the Lord of Life, <hi>The Prince of Life, Act. 3. 15. The Lord of the Living, and of the Dead, Rom.</hi> 14. 9. He is the Lord of Life For Efficiency, Our Life comes from Him who is our Life; and For Authority, The Keyes of Life are in his Hands. If Any of you be the Lord or Maſter of a Servant; as that Servant may expect Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Suſtenance, and Reward from you; ſo do you expect and challenge Obedience and Service from him. His Work is yours<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> His Trading is yours, His Gaining is yours; All the Stock which he em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploys
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117743:12"/>
is your Stock, and it is employed for your Advantage: The Lord is the End of the Servants Life: And ſo muſt Jeſus Chriſt (who is the Lord of Life, and the Lord of your Lives) be the End of your Lives; For He is <hi>Your Lord, 2 Pet.</hi> 1. 2. And you are <hi>Chriſts Servants, 1 Cor.</hi> 7. 22. Your whole ſtock of Life is from his Grace, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is to be layd out for his Glory.</p>
            <p n="3">3. All the Spiritual Principles of Life, which are conferred upon you, do encline and enable you to live unto Chriſt, to ſet up Chriſt, to act for him, and to exalt him: And they are given for this end, that you ſhould be the Servants of his Glory; and in their proper ſphere do move for this very end, to ſhew forth the Praiſes of him who hath called you. I will inſtance in a Few of them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Unto you is Given Precious Faith. And what is the Natural Labor of Faith, but to Set the Crown on the Head of Chriſt? To Glorifie Jeſus Chriſt? Faith makes you to Forſake All for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and to Beſtow All on Chriſt, who Beſtows His All on you.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Unto you is Given a Superlative Love of Chriſt. <hi>Saw ye Him whom my Soul loveth?</hi> ſaid the Church, <hi>Cantic. 3. 3. Thou Knoweſt that I love thee,</hi> ſaid <hi>Peter, Ioh.</hi> 21. 17. O Lord Jeſus, ſaid <hi>Bernard,</hi> I love thee more then All my Goods, <note place="margin">Pluſquam mea, pluſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quamme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, pluſquam me.</note> and I love thee more then All my Friends, yea, I love thee more then All my Self. Now you know that <hi>Love ſeeks not her own, 1 Cor.</hi> 13. 5. All the powers and ſervices of Love are His, whom we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117743:12"/>
love: His we Are, and For Him we Are, whom we do love.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Unto you is Given Humble Self-denial. And what are Humility and Self-denial, but the Footſtool of Jeſus Chriſt? But your ſelves in a dark Cloud, that Chriſt above may ſhine in Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? You in Nothing, and Chriſt in All? You in Service, and Chriſt in Praiſe? None but Chriſt for your Confidence, and None but Chriſt for your End.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Unto you is Given Burning Zeal. And what is that Zeal, but a Flame for his Cauſe and Glory? <hi>Whether we be beſides our ſelves, it is to God, 2 Cor.</hi> 5. 13. All the Activities and Enlargements of Zeal are put forth in Services for Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Of All People, you who are Real Chriſtians have the moſt forcible and cogent Obligations to reſolve your Lives unto Jeſus Chriſt; For whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever may emphatically engage Any to Reſpects and Services, that takes Abundant hold on you to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs theſe unto Chriſt. O Chriſtians! What is not Chriſt to you? What hath not Chriſt done for you? What hath not Chriſt ſuffered for you? What will not Chriſt do for you? and what is that weight of Glory which you ſhall have from your Chriſt, after that you have done a little more weak Services for your Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Chriſt is Life to you, and Love to you, and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to you, and Peace to you, and Righteouſneſs to you, and Sanctification to you, and Redemption to you, and Help to you, and Hope to you. He is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117743:13"/>
your Friend, He is your Saviour, He is your Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, He is your Chriſt to the utmoſt, For All, For ever and For ever! All that ever he did, and All that He is Now doing, and All which ever he will do, All this hath a ſpecial and peculiar Reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Serviceableneſs to your Good, to your ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Good. Why then, Eye for Eye, and Love for Love, and Service for Service, and Life for Life again. <hi>Thou haſt Redeemed us to God by thy Blood, and haſt made us unto our God, Kings and Priests: And therefore worthy is the Lamb to Receive Power, and Riches, and Wiſdom, and Strength, and Honor, and Glory, and Bleſsing, Rev.</hi> 5. 9, 10, 12.</p>
            <p>Nay, let me add one Obligation more which lies upon you, and that is this; You are the onely Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the world, whom Jeſus Chriſt doth intruſt with his Glorious Intereſts: He forms you for his Praiſe, he truſts you with All his Honor here below amongſt the ſons of men. And truly, as it is your Great Honor to be truſted with the Honor of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> So are you thereby the more obliged to live and act for his Honor and Glory.</p>
            <p n="5">5. To direct and act the whole Courſe of Life for Chriſt; This is the Higheſt and Nobleſt Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of Life. Beloved! Our Actions have their denominations, partly from their Formal and intrinſecal cauſe, and partly from their Final and extrinſecal cauſe. The Actions of Man are more Noble then thoſe of Irrational Creatures, becauſe They do flow from a Cauſe, from a Soul, which is more Noble. And the Actions of a Chriſtian are
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117743:13"/>
more Noble then thoſe of a Man, becauſe they do ſpring from Principles which are divine. And as Actions are thus dignified by their Formal Cauſes, ſo likewiſe are They by their Final and Extrinſecal Cauſes. The more low and ſordid the Ends are, the more baſe are the Actions of Life; As when they are unworthy of ſuch a ſtate and condition. If a Man ſhould form his courſe of Life onely for ſuch ends which do bound the Appetites of Brute Beaſts, in ſatisfying of himſelf with Senſual Objects, this ſordid End makes his Life a moſt ſordid Life. And ſo on the contrary, the more excellent the Ends are for which our Lives are improved, the more are our Lives raiſed in the degrees of Beauty and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. The more perfect Ends do always grace our Actions with the more perfect Glory. The Actions of God himſelf are therefore the moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, becauſe they are Levelled at, and come up moſt perfectly to His own Glory, which is the chief End of Himſelf. And ſo it is with the Actions of our Lives, when they Riſe to Chriſt, and are Termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in him; This is their Dignity and Glory, they cannot be Raiſed unto a more choyce Nature or degree of employment; They are Now carried on and lifted up to the higheſt End. As far as <hi>Chriſt</hi> and His Glory are above Sinful Luſts and Worldly Luſts, above Earthly Pleaſures and Earthly Profits, and Earthly Honors, and above our Selves; So Far is a Living unto Chriſt above and beyond a Living unto Any or All of theſe.</p>
            <p>And thus have you heard the Firſt Propoſition in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117743:14"/>
ſome meaſure cleared unto you, Namely, That the Life of a Chriſtian is Reſolved into Chriſt. I Now come to ſpeak of the ſecond Propoſition, which is this,</p>
            <p>That the Death of a Chriſtian is Reſolved into <note place="margin">2 <hi>Propo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it.</hi>
               </note> Gain, <hi>[To me to live, is Chriſt, And to dye, is Gain.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not trouble you with the ſeveral conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations of Gain, which yet might be aptly applied to the preſent Subject; As <hi>(Lucrum ex Benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia, ex Pacto, ex Societate, ex Re Accepta,)</hi> Gain by Favor, by Compact, by Society, by Matter fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into hand, in reſpect of all which the Chriſtian is a Gainer by Death. But I ſhall briefly clear the Aſſertion, 1. By Scriptures. 2. By Arguments.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By Scriptures. <hi>Eccleſiaſtes 7. 1. The day of Death is better then the day of ones Birth.</hi> If it be Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then it is Gain. If you get more by Death then you do by Life, ſurely then Death is a Gain. <hi>Phil. 1. 23. I have a deſire to depart, (i. e.)</hi> to dye, (Death to a Godly man is but a departure from one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to another, and from one place to another,) <hi>and to be with Chriſt, which is far Better.</hi> To be In <note place="margin">
                  <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum cum Paulo, magna ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitas; Eſſe Paul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um cum Chriſto<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſumma Felicitas.</hi> Bernard.</note> Chriſt, is very Good; thus we are whiles we live: But to be With Chriſt, this is Beſt of All; and thus we are when we dye. For Chriſt to be with <hi>Paul,</hi> this was a Great Bleſſing; But for <hi>Paul</hi> to be with Chriſt, this was chiefeſt Bleſſedneſs, ſaid <hi>Bernard.</hi> Take one place more, <hi>Revel. 14. 13. Bleſſed Are the Dead which dye in the Lord, they reſt from their
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117743:14"/>
labors, and their works Follow them.</hi> There is a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of Bleſſedneſs which Chriſtians have in this Life, But the Full Portion of it is at Death; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Death is Gain. In this Life we are laboring for Bleſſedneſs, but at Death you ſhall be Fully poſſeſſed of Bleſſedneſs. Poſſeſſion is better then Expectation, and Bleſſedneſs in Hand is better then Bleſſedneſs in Hope; therefore Death is Gain to Chriſtians.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By Arguments. It cannot be, but that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians muſt Needs Gain by Death, Becauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they paſs into ſuch an Eſtate, where they do receive a Full Reward, and where All the Promiſes of God are perfectly made Good unto them, and where All the Gracious and Eternal Intentions of Love and Happineſs towards them, are (as in their laſt End) Fulfilled and Accompliſhed. And beyond which Eſtate there is Not in them, No Not a poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible capacity for the Fruition of a Greater Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and Glory.</p>
            <p>But more particularly; If the Eſtate, into which the Chriſtian is Tranſlated by Death, doth more then Recompence All his Loſſes by Death, and doth tranſcendently exceed All the Benefits which he hath in Life; then Death is Gain or Advantage un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: For herein doth All Gain conſiſt; It is a Fuller Recompence, or a Larger Addition. If you loſe a little, and for that Receive more, this is Gain. If you lay out a little, and for this Take in much, this alſo is Gain. Now conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Chriſtians Compenſations by Death are
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117743:15"/>
far greater then any of his Loſſes by Death. You read of the <hi>Phoenix,</hi> that her old Age falling into the Flames of death, procures unto her a ſecond Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Birth of a New and Freſh Life; And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Death is an Advantage unto that Creature. Much more is it to the Chriſtian, concerning whom the Apoſtle ſaith in 2 <hi>Cor. 5. 4. That Mortality is ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up of Life,</hi> and that <hi>Death is but the diſſolving of his Earthly houſe,</hi> ſo that he might enjoy <hi>An houſe Not made with Hand, Eternal in the Heavens:</hi> Verſ. 1.</p>
            <p>There is Nothing which you can loſe by Death, but what muſt be loſt, and what (for the moſt part) may be loſt in Life. And whatſoever that is which you ſo loſe by Death, it is ſuperabundantly made up unto you again. You loſe a Mortal Life, but then you Finde an Immortal Life: You loſe the Society of Men, but then you Finde the Society of Angels: You loſe the Sight of Friends, but then you Finde the Sight of God: You loſe the Poſſeſſion of the World, but then you Finde the Poſſeſſion of the Kingdom of Heaven. Are Not theſe Compenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons more then Equivalent to your Loſſes? Do they Not Infinitely exceed them? The people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> quit <hi>Egypt (the Houſe of Bondage,)</hi> and poſſeſs <hi>Canaan (the Land of Promiſe;)</hi> Would you call this a Loſs, which exceeds All that was enjoyed in <hi>Egypt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O Chriſtian! The leaſt Good in Heaven (if there be Any thing there which can be called The l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt Good!) Far ſurmounts All the Good from
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117743:15"/>
which Death can part you here on Earth. The Candle is out, I, But Now thou Haſt the Sun! I leave my Earthly Father, I, but I Now Go to my Heavenly Father! I part with my Husband, O but I Go to my Chriſt! The Streams are cut off, O but Now I am at the Fountain! I ſhall Never meet with Creature-comforts more, O but I ſhall Now enjoy Him who makes All Comforts, and who is All Comforts, God, My God; Chriſt, My Chriſt for ever.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Chriſtians Eſtate Receives a larger Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Death, and therefore for him to dye is Gain. There are three things added unto your Eſtate by Death, which you longed to have, but Never might, Nor could enjoy in this Life: 1. An Abſolute Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy. 2. A Perfect Fruition. 3. An Invariable Eternity.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Chriſtian hath this Gain by Death, That it proves an Abſolute Remedy: Death doth that for Him in One Moment, which All the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Chriſt could Never do, which All the Graces of the Spirit could Never do, which All the Joys of the Holy Ghoſt could Never do: It doth inſtantly cure his Soul and Body; It doth perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cure them and deliver them From All the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of Life, from All the Troubles of Life, from All Infirmities and Diſeaſes in the Body, from All Sinful Corruptions in the Soul, from All the Temptations and Aſſaults of Satan; All theſe are at their end, when Life is at an end. And truly to loſe All theſe, and All theſe for ever, is deſervedly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117743:16"/>
to be Reckoned amongſt Our Gains and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages.</p>
            <p>I have Read of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, that he did once ask a Philoſopher, How long a Man ſhould de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ire to live, who anſwered, Until he thinks it better to dye, then to live. Is it Not Better to dye, and to be rid of All Sin, to dye, and be rid of All Temptations, to dye, and be rid of All Miſeries, then to live, and carry about us a Body of Sin, which ſo often darkens our Light, grieves our God, and troubles our Conſciences?</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Chriſtian hath this Gain by Death, Not onely that he hath the Better of the contrary Eſtates, but alſo that by Death he p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſeth from an Imperfect Good Eſtate, unto a Perfect Good Eſtate: He Now comes to be of Full Age, and to be a Full Poſſeſſor. One ſays, That This <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> Life, This Preſent Life, is Not <hi>Vita, ſed Via ad Vitam,</hi> It is Not Life, but a Motion, a Journey towards Life. He ſpeaks it of the Natural Life, but we may raiſe it even to the Spiritual Life of a Chriſtian: His Spiritual Life (comparatively con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered) is rather <hi>Via,</hi> then <hi>Vita;</hi> a ſtep towards Life, then Life. Compare All which you are poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of, as Beleeving Chriſtians, in this Life, with All that of which you ſhall be poſſeſſed in that other Life, you may ſpeak of them what <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake of the Two Miniſtrations, <hi>Even that which was made Glorious had No Glory in this reſpect, by reaſon of the Glory that excelleth, 2 Cor.</hi> 3. 10. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſame Apoſtle, comparing the Preſent
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117743:16"/>
Condition of Grace with that Future Condition of Glory, ſaith, <hi>Now we ſee through a Glaſs, darkly, But Then Face to Face: Now I Know in part, But Then I ſhall Know even as alſo I Am Known, 1 Cor.</hi> 13. 12. Look how Great the Diſproportion is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a dark and a clear Seeing, and between our Knowing of God, and Gods Knowing of Us, the one being very Imperfect, and the other being very Abſolute; So Great is the Diſproportion of the preſent Condition of Spiritual Life on Earth to that Glorified Life in Heaven. 'Tis true, you have the ſame God on Earth, which you ſhall have in Heaven; and you have the ſame Chriſt on Earth, which you ſhall have in Heaven! But yet your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with Him, and your Fruition of Him in Heaven, is wonderfully more perfect and exquiſite, then it is, or can be, here on Earth. His Manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Himſelf to your Souls, and your Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of thoſe Manifeſtations, are moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly Enlarged You ſhall then Know, and Love, and Enjoy your God, even as much as Glorified Souls can Know, and can Love, and can Enjoy a God. And God himſelf diſcovers as much of Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf unto your Souls, as will make them perfectly Bleſſed, and Fully Happy, in the clear Viſion and Fruition of Himſelf. Now this Addition, perfect Addition to Our Eſtate (occaſioned by Death) doth plainly prove, That to dye, is Gain. You ſhall Never Reign, till you dye: You ſhall Never Know as you are Known, you ſhall Never Apprehend as you are Apprehended, you ſhall Never be at Home,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117743:17"/>
you ſhall Never come to a Perfect Holineſs, to a Perfect Sight, to a Perfect Full Fruition, Never be Perfectly Filled up, Until you Dye.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Chriſtian hath yet one more Exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of His Eſtate by Death, and that is, an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>variable Eternity. Whatſoever the Chriſtian <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inds in Himſelf in this Life, for the Habituals of Grace, It is Imperfect; and whatſoever he findes for the Comfortables of Grace, It is very Various: Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it is More, and ſometimes it is Leſs; Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it is High, and ſometimes it is Low, and Sometimes it is None at all. Sometimes Heaven is opened, and Sometimes the Viſion is drawn up, and Heaven is ſhut. One while he ſees the Face of God, and Rejoyceth; Another while God Hides his Face, and then he is Troubled: But by Death he comes to a Fixed and Invariable Eternity; He ſhall Ever be with the Lord: And as the Angels, ſo ſhall He always behold the Face of his Father. O Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans! It is always Day in Heaven, There the Sun ſtill ſhines in Strength and Beauty, and Never Sets, and Never Declines; Thy Joy ſhall be an Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Joy, Never Interrupted, Never Eclipſed, Never Diminiſhed; Full at once, and Full for ever! Eternal Happineſs, Happy Eternity! Perfect Fruition and Eternal Fruition! Perfect Pleaſure, and Eternal Pleaſure! As long as God is God, ſo long will your Compleat Happineſs be, and abide in your God for ever, and ever, and ever.</p>
            <p>And Now having caſt up All Accounts, Tell me whether you may not ſay with <hi>Paul, To me to Dye,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117743:17"/>
is Gain?</hi> I have read a Fancy of one <hi>Trophonius,</hi> that when he had Built and Dedicated that goodly Temple at <hi>Delphos,</hi> asked of <hi>Apollo</hi> (for his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence) That Thing which was Beſt for Man! The Oracle willed him to Go home, and within Three days he ſhould have it, and within that Time he dyed. O Chriſtian! The Beſt thing on Earth is to live ſo, as to Get into Chriſt; But the Beſt thing of All is to dye, and to be with Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I have done with both the Doctrinal Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from the Text; There remains Nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde, but the uſeful Applications of the whole unto our Selves.</p>
            <p>Is the Life of a Real Chriſtian Reſolved into <note place="margin">1 <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi>
               </note> Chriſt? Then I Fear that there Are But Few Real Chriſtians in the World. What Chriſt ſpake of the Way which did lead to Life, <hi>Few there be that Finde it, Mat.</hi> 7. 14. That I may ſpeak of Chriſt, as the Scope of our Life, Few there be who make Him ſo, and minde Him as ſo. <hi>All ſeek their own, Not the Things which Are Jeſus Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts;</hi> Thus the Apoſtle long ſince (and ſo may it Now be) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 21.</p>
            <p>If we did faithfully caſt up All the Ages of Life, and All the Services and Disburſements of thoſe Ages, What (think you) would, in the Foot of the whole account, Fall unto the ſhare of Chriſt?</p>
            <p>"That Age of Infancy is found to be but a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher: We Know not what it was, Nor for whom it was; it was a meer Fancy of Life.</p>
            <p>"That Age of Youth is found to be but a Vanity:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117743:18"/>
A Vain Life it is, and if layd out on Any thing, that ſame Goes wholy upon the account of Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, which is the Bane and Madneſs of Life.</p>
            <p>"That Age of Manhood is found to be but the Death of Life: therein men Serve their luſts, weary themſelves in their Iniquities, give up themſelves to Sin with greedineſs; this is the Reproach and Loſs of Life.</p>
            <p>"That Age of Old-Age, wherein the Grave is digging for Life, wherein the Glaſs is even run out, and the Candle is ſpent to the laſt inch; yet this Age, where Men are ſtepping out of the World, is that Age wherein Men moſt dote on the World, and are Scraping for the things of this Life. And thus, either Nothing hath our Lives, or Vanity (which is the beſt of Nothing) hath our Lives; Or Sin (which is worſe then Nothing) hath our Lives; Or the World (which is little better then Nothing) hath our Lives: And Jeſus Chriſt (who is the Beſt of All things) hath no ſhare at all; or if any, it is the laſt, the leaſt, the dregs and ſnuffs of our Lives.</p>
            <p>This I ſpeak onely in the general: but give me Favor to Preſs this ſad Conviction a little cloſer unto our Selves. There are Four ſorts of men, who do not live to Chriſt; They cannot ſay, <hi>To me to live, is Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Spiritually dead men, unconverted men; It is impoſſible to live to Chriſt, until Chriſt doth firſt live in us. Chriſt cannot be the End of Life, where He is not the Principle of Life. It is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117743:18"/>
Expreſſion which <hi>Ambroſe</hi> hath, That is not a Death, but Life, which Joyns the Dying <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ambroſius in 1 Tim.</hi> 5 6.</note> Man to Chriſt; and that is Not a Life, but Death, which Separates the Living Man from Chriſt. Now, how many men are there who have not the Life of Chriſt in them? Nay, who are Alienated from the Life of Chriſt, are dead in treſpaſſes and ſins?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Self-Intereſted men, who live wholy unto themſelves. The Apoſtle ſpeaks of Some who are <hi>Lovers of themſelves, 2 Tim.</hi> 3. 2. and who are Seekers of themſelves, <hi>Philip.</hi> 2. 21. and who are Minders of themſelves; <hi>They minde Earthly things, Phil.</hi> 3. 19. Of all theſe we may ſay, as God ſpake of <hi>Iſrael, Iſrael is An Empty Vine, he brings forth Fruit unto Himſelf, Hoſea</hi> 10. 1. Theſe men are ſo far from living unto Chriſt, that they would for Self ends make a Living of Chriſt himſelf.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Offenſive men, who live to the Diſhonor and Reproach of Chriſt. <hi>Many walk, of whom I have told you often, and Now tell you even weeping, that they are the Enemies of the Croſs of Chriſt, Phil.</hi> 3. 18. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in Name, but not in Life; in Life they are the Enemies of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Salvian</hi> relates how the Heathen did Reproach ſome Chriſtians, who by Their lewd lives made the Goſpel of Chriſt to be a Reproach: Where (ſaid <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Salvianus de G. D.</hi> l. 4.</note> they) is that Good Law which they do Beleeve? Where are thoſe Rules of Godlineſs which they do learn? They read the Holy Goſpel, and yet are Unclean; They Hear the Apoſtles Writings, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117743:19"/>
yet are Drunk; They Follow Chriſt, and yet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey Chriſt; They profeſs a Pure Law, and yet do lead Impure Lives. O Sirs! A wicked Life in a Chriſtian is ſo far from living unto Chriſt, that it is a Blaſpheming of Chriſt, and a Crucifying of Chriſt, and putting of him to open ſhame.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Dull and unſenſible men; of ſuch did one long ſince complain, That they did <hi>(Patientiùs ferre Chriſti Jacturam, quam Suam)</hi> more calmly paſs by the Injuries done to Chriſt, then thoſe which were done unto themſelves. Many men do carry themſelves towards the Blaſphemous Diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of Chriſt, as the Prieſts did to the heavy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of <hi>Judas,</hi> What is that to us? See thou to that! Although they do Know how much the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſt, and the Truths of Chriſt, and the Ordinances of Chriſt, are oppoſed and contemned; yet they lay None of theſe things to Heart: They paſs by the Wounded man; they ſpeak not for Chriſt, ſtand not for Chriſt, act not their Parts and Power for Chriſt. Is this your Love to Chriſt? Is this your Care for Chriſt? Is this to live to Chriſt? Can you ever anſwer Chriſt for this?</p>
            <p>But I paſs on; Is the Life of a Real Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved <note place="margin">2 <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi>
               </note> unto Chriſt? Then let us every one ſtrive ſo to live, ſo to employ and improve Life, that Chriſt may be magnified by us. You Read, That <hi>the Four and Twenty Elders Fell down before Him that ſate on the Throne, and worſhipped Him that liveth for ever and ever; And did caſt Their Crowns before the Thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne, ſaying, Thou Art Worthy, O Lord, to Receive
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117743:19"/>
Glory, and Honor, and Power, for Thou haſt Created All things, and for Thy Pleaſure they Are, and were Created, Revel.</hi> 4. 10, 11. So let Every one of us Proſtrate All our Excellencies, and All our Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, All our Places, and Powers, and Endevors, to the Honor and Glory of Jeſus Chriſt. If we had a more clear and experimental Knowledg of the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing Love of Chriſt, we would do ſo! That would Endear our Hearts to Chriſt, That would Inflame our Hearts for Chriſt; It would make us to ſpend and to be ſpent for Chriſt! O that you, who are Parliament-men, would live more for Chriſt! Who amongſt us have ſuch Power, and ſuch Opportunities to do for Chriſt, as you have? God ſpeaks Honorably of <hi>Phineas, He was Zealous for my ſake, Numb.</hi> 25. 11. And Chriſt commends <hi>Epheſus, For my Names ſake thou haſt Labored, and haſt not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ainted, Revel.</hi> 2. 3. Put out your Selves againſt Blaſphemies and Profaneneſs, and put out your Selves for All the Ordinances, Truths, and Ways of Chriſt, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>O that you, who are Magiſtrates of this City, would live more to Chriſt! Do more for Chriſt! Be more vigorous in Puniſhing and Reſtraining the open Profanations of the Lords Day, Notorious Drunkenneſſes and Abominations! Encourage and ſupport All the Intereſts of Chriſt!</p>
            <p>O that you, who are the Embaſſadors of Chriſt, would live more to Chriſt! Do you deſire to Know Nothing but Jeſus Chriſt, and Him Crucified? Reveal the Glorious Excellencies of Chriſt, make
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117743:20"/>
Know the unſpeakable Love of Chriſt, direct men, ſtrive with men, perſwade men to Know Chriſt, to come into Chriſt, to ſerve Chriſt. What have you more to do, then to be doing for Chriſt?</p>
            <p>O that All of us would live more to Chriſt! That All our Oyl might be emptied into the Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Candleſtick! That Parents and Children, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Servants, All might be doing more for Chriſt! Every Morning let us conſider, What may I do this day for Chriſt? Every Evening let us Review, What have I done this day for Chriſt? And as he thought that day loſt, wherein he had done No Good thing; So let us repute that part of Life as dead and loſt, wherein we have done No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the Honor and Advantage of Chriſt. O Chriſtian! Thou liveſt not; until thou liveſt to Chriſt. O Chriſtian! Thou canſt not dye, but thou muſt dye for ever, if thou haſt not lived unto Chriſt. It was a Good Speech of one, <hi>(Vis in pace mori? ſis Servus Dei;)</hi> Wouldſt thou dye in Peace? then be the Servant of God. So ſay I, Wouldſt thou dye, and Go to Chriſt? then live ſo, as to be a Servant of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Every Man, when he dyes, Goes unto his Maſter whom he hath ſerved, and to whom he hath lived. A Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ked Man, when he dyes, he goes to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter whom he hath ſerved; He goes to the Devil, and to the Place of Torment. A Godly Man, when he dyes, he goes to His Maſter, He goes to His Chriſt, and enters into the Joy of his Maſter. If you would dye with <hi>Pauls</hi> Confidence, you muſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117743:20"/>
firſt live with <hi>Pauls</hi> Conſcience. <hi>I have fought A Good Fight, I have finiſhed my Courſe, I have Kept the Faith:</hi> Here is <hi>Pauls</hi> Conſcience. <hi>Henceforth there is layd up for me A Crown of Righteouſneſs, &amp;c.</hi> Here is <hi>Pauls</hi> Confidence: 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 7, 8.</p>
            <p>O Bleſſed Chriſt! Be Thou my Maſter, make me thy Servant! Let me grieve that I have done ſo little for thee, let me pray that I may do more for thee. When Death comes, my work is at an end; I can then Never Speak more, Nor do more for Thee, who haſt done ſo much for me. O that I could live many days in one day, and many lives in one life! The time is ſhort, the Reward is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite; let my remaining life be No longer mine, but thine; At leaſt let this be found in me, That I would ſerve none but thy Self; and that though o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may exceed me in Acting for thy Glory, yet None may exceed me in Sincerity of Endevor to be Altogether Thine.</p>
            <p>And thus have I ſaid Something of the Beſt Life, and of the Beſt Death; To live is Chriſt, To dye is Gain. I will borrow a little more of your Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Speak a few words to the Preſent Occaſion, concerning our Brother departed, who whiles he lived could ſay, <hi>To me to live, is Chriſt;</hi> and being Now dead, hath found the other truth of the Text, <hi>To me to dye, is Gain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His manner of Life from his youth, moſt, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you here preſent, do Know; And therefore I ſhall ſay the leſs of him, of whom you Knew ſo well, and ſo much.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:117743:21"/>There were three things, three choyce Jewels, which were very Remarkable in him, beſides All the reſt: The Firſt was Humility, the Beauty of Graces. The Second was Integrity, the Soul of Graces. The Third was Faith, the Crown of Graces.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He was an Humble Chriſtian under All thoſe Eminent Places of Service unto which He was call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. For one who lived ſo ſhort a ſpace of Time (He lived not above Thirty Six years in all) He was Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to as many, and (as the Times Now are) to as Great Places of Employment, as Any of His Rank (I think) in the Land; To be a <hi>Parliament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> To be of the <hi>Councel of State,</hi> To be a <hi>Juſtice</hi> in the Country, To be an <hi>Alderman,</hi> and <hi>Sheriff</hi> of This Great City, &amp;c. Under All which weight of Advancements He deported himſelf with a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet and lowly ſpirit, Not lifted up, Not at all loſing himſelf, Nor Altered by Any of theſe Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations. Theſe things were under Him, Not above Him; and truly he looked on them as Burthens, and Cares, and Greater Duties; Not as Dignities and Poor Glories. It is Not an eaſie matter to bear a low condition with a contented minde; No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yet an High condition with a lowly Heart. It ſhews a ſtrength of Grace to be Patient in Troubles, and to be Humble in Dignities.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He was a Sincere Chriſtian: Active and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere. His Integrity was Anſwerable unto his Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. In all His Places waſting his Life for the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Good: Doing much Good, but Scraping up
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:117743:21"/>
Nothing to his Private Good. The Publique did not ſerve Him, but He did ſerve the Publique: He was the Servant, Not the Executor, of the Land. He might truly ſay, as once <hi>Samuel</hi> did, <hi>Behold here I am, witneſs Againſt me, Whoſe Ox have I Taken? or whoſe Aſs have I taken? or whom have I defraud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? whom have I oppreſſed? or of whoſe hand have I received Any Bribe, to blinde mine eyes therewith? 1 Sam.</hi> 12. 3.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He was a Beleeving Chriſtian: prizing and exalting <hi>Chriſt</hi> Above All, and Rejoycing in <hi>Chriſt</hi> as in His onely Beſt of All; Nay, often expoſing his very life, Jeoparding it in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>igh places of the Field, Not counting it too dear for <hi>Chriſt</hi> and His Cauſe.</p>
            <p>But, as one ſpake well, Seldom is Excellency in Any Kinde long-liv'd. When we ſee Men Abund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly layd out for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and Acting for Him, It is an Ordinary Symptome, That they have Not much time left to do for Chriſt. When a Perſon is High in Grace, He is Nigh to Glory; the Nearer the Center, the Swifter Motion. And thus it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fel him: His days were Fulfilled even in the midſt of his days. Weakneſs and Sickneſs ſuddenly ſeize on him, and at length tranſlate him to be with His Chriſt, which is beſt of All. And all theſe Death-ſummons and Death-ſtrokes he did Bear with that Heavenly Patience, and ſweet compoſedneſs of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that as the Jews <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eign of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Soul, That it was Suck'd out of his mouth with Kiſſes; So His Soul did Kindly take leave of His Body, that, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:117743:22"/>
a Metaphor or <hi>Hyperbole,</hi> His Death was but a Sleep and Reſt.</p>
            <p>And Here, by the way, ſuffer me (as a Friend) to ſpeak for him, who cannot Now ſpeak for himſelf, In Taking off that Falſhood, Bold and Notorious Falſhood, Raiſed on him by That Generation of Lyars, even whiles he was yet living, and able to confute it, himſelf; As <hi>Luther</hi> did the lying Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals of the Papiſts, concerning his ſtrange hideous Death and Burial.</p>
            <p>Some had Raiſed on him, at the beginning of his weakneſs, That he was Fallen mad, and they Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign the Particular Occaſion of it; Then both which Nothing could be more Falſly ſaid. The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Truth is, That he was of a compoſed Minde to the very laſt Gaſp, and ſo compoſedly Himſelf, that within a Few hours before his Death, he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected his own Will with his own Hand.</p>
            <p>But This is an old malicious Trick of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, to oppoſe Good Men, living, and to reproach Good Men dying, and dead. Jeſus Chriſt could Not Eſcape it in his Life, Nor yet when layd in his Grave. No more could the Apoſtles of Chriſt, Nor the Primitive Chriſtians, Nor thoſe Eminent Servants of Chriſt againſt Popery, <hi>Hus, Wicliff, Luther, Calvin, Oecolampadius, Beza, Junius, &amp;c.</hi> Nor yet many Glorious Inſtruments in our own days.</p>
            <p>The Servant is Not Above his Maſter: If Chriſt himſelf were Accounted Mad, it muſt Not ſeem harſh, Nor ſtrange, that Any of his Servants be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:117743:22"/>
ſo. And beſides this, it is alſo a Comfort to Good Men when None ſpeak evil of them, but evil men; Nor can theſe ſpeak evil of them without a lye, as <hi>Jerom</hi> hath it. And truly it is a Sure Sign, that there is ſomething of Great Worth in that Man, whoſe Name wicked men do ſtrive ſo much to aſperſe and wound. The Dogs bark moſt, when the Traveller Gallops.</p>
            <p>But let theſe poor ſpirited men have leave to pleaſe themſelves, who have no other weapon, but a lye and a Reproach, left to Revenge themſelves. This is the Truth, Our departed Brother lived in Faith, and dyed in Peace. If in Any thing he might truly be ſaid Not to be Himſelf, it was onely in this, That He was Not his Own, but Chriſts.</p>
            <p>And ſo I have done with him, and with you, ſave that I have a Word to them who ſtood in Near Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation unto him. I confeſs your loſs is Great, but let this comfort you, that ſo His Gain is alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Great. You have more cauſe to Rejoyce that you had ſuch a Husband, and ſuch a Son, then you have to Grieve that God hath Taken him from you. He is but Gone before, you muſt ſhortly Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. In the mean time make up All your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts in God. Though theſe Outward Comforts dye, yet the God of All Comforts lives for ever<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Sun ſtill ſhines, though the Glaſs-windows be broken.</p>
            <p>And let us All here at this time Go away the Better. We muſt Every one, ere long, dye, and come to Judgment, and Give an Account of our
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:117743:23"/>
Life. Live ſo, that you may live for ever; and dye ſo, that you may dye but once. You Are Servants, and I truſt Chriſts Servants: Be doing the Work of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and be Faithful in That Work of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Bleſſed is that Servant, whom His Maſter, when He cometh, ſhall Finde So Doing, and So Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing!</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
